<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The faithful testimony of High-Hall detected and the examen, of the pretences and character of Mr. William Russel, &amp;c. vindicated. Part I.</title>
            <author>Gale, Nathaniel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23372</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833909</idno>
  <idno type="VID">206806</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248541425</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing G132</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833909</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99833909e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23372)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 206806)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1830:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The faithful testimony of High-Hall detected and the examen, of the pretences and character of Mr. William Russel, &amp;c. vindicated. Part I.</title>
                  <author>Gale, Nathaniel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Nathaniel Gale.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Russel, William, d. 1702 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Examen, of the pretences and character of Mr. William Russel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:206806:1"/>
            <p>THE Faithful Testimony OF <hi>HIGH-HALL</hi> DETECTED; AND THE <hi>EXAMEN,</hi> Of the Pretences and Character OF Mr. <hi>WILLIAM RƲSSEL,</hi> &amp;c. VINDICATED.</p>
            <p>Part I.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:206806:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:206806:2"/>
            <head>THE Faithful Testimony OF <hi>HIGH—HALL</hi> DETECTED, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE different Colours, the <hi>Faithful Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> as 'tis called, appear'd in (when it saluted the light of our <hi>Meridian,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing crept out of the Darkest Cranny, and vilest Harbour for the worst of Filth in all <hi>Cow-Lane</hi>) to the Eyes of those Concern'd, upon the various Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions and Ideas they had of the Matters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: it being either enfeebled by bright Rays, streaming from all Parts of the enlightned <hi>Hemisphere;</hi> and so easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repulsed and beat back again into the <hi>Infernal Place</hi> from whence it took its <hi>Original:</hi> Or the Eyes of the over Credulous and fondly Partial occaecated by the <hi>Pretence</hi> and <hi>Obscurity</hi> of that <hi>trifling</hi> and confused <hi>Piece;</hi> have provoked my Zeal and Charity to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to dispel the Mist from the Eyes of these clouded and deceived Souls, and set 'em in a clear light; that so they may not be imposed upon; nor <hi>Religion</hi> suffer, for want of being ascertain'd of Mr. <hi>Russel</hi>'s nefarious and abominable Actions; and of the Baseness or great Indiscretion of those that favour and uphold him.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:206806:3"/>
            <p>Well might the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Examen</hi> lament the great Decay of <hi>Religion,</hi> and the loss of its pristine <hi>Purity,</hi> when the most notorious Immoralities and unheard of Villanies, are extenuated and connived at; and the Actors of 'em countenanced and defended, particularly, by Two Persons of considerable Name and Figure in the Profession of <hi>Christianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So hot a Zeal have these Men for their own <hi>Sys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tems,</hi> and so <hi>Dogmatically</hi> bent to support 'em; they are even stupified by the viollent Heat and Fury of their own Lightning and Thunder, and seem unsen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, that to run Riot, and swim in all manner of Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suality, is so much as a venial Crime: Or if they do, to be <hi>Orthodox,</hi> that is to Believe as they'd have, will expiate the Offence, and all their Immora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities will have no weight in the Ballance, to either <hi>we are all subject to Failings,</hi> or <hi>they are Chapions for Religion, Patronizers of the Faith, Detectors of Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, Idolatrous</hi> and <hi>Damnable Heresies of</hi> Cassin <hi>and his Abettors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Sirs; Whoredom, Lying and Drunkenness, are certainly damnable Sins; and ten times more Infectious, Dishonourable and Dangerous to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than a Thousand Errors of truly Sincere and Conscientious Christians. And as for Mr. <hi>Cassin's</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they have been Proved in the <hi>Examen</hi> not Fundamental, nor Voluntary Errors, such as he is not Wilfully Guilty of, because he Acts to the best of his Understanding, all which will be farther consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in a Second Part, if we find occasion for it; but here I shall only evidence the Truth of the Matters charged on the Doctor in the <hi>Examen;</hi> and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect their Unfaithful Testimony.</p>
            <p>Upon the Publication of their <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> the <hi>Person</hi> charged with Methodizing the <hi>Examen,</hi> was much of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ended at the <hi>Calumnies</hi> and the <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgery</hi> they had cast up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, which he had heard of, from several Hands,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:206806:3"/> and thought himself obliged in Justice to vindicate his Innocency and Reputation. To which End it being absolutely necessary for him to see the pretended <hi>Faithful Testimony,</hi> apply'd himself to a Certain <hi>Person</hi> he took to be his <hi>Friend</hi> and a <hi>Familiar</hi> of the <hi>Doctors,</hi> by whose means he hoped to obtain one or more of them; But how it came about, whether by his Friends Indiscretion or Perfidy, the <hi>Doctor</hi> came acquainted by whom he was employ'd; so that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of a <hi>Book,</hi> he received; the <hi>Dr.</hi> did not owe Mr. — so much Service, nor did he know what Business he had with them; unless to Burn. An An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer too uncharitable, tho we should suppose the <hi>Doctor</hi> sensible, that they deserve Fire and Faggot. However it is Evident by this Denyal, he resolved to prevent as much as he could their being Burnt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were read, as some did the <hi>Examen;</hi> an Instance that some Men were bent to Vindicate and Uphold him Right or Wrong. But farther, that if Mr.— himself would come, he would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him a Book or Two. But Mr. — it seems ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chose to send him a short Letter with the Causes (in general) and Reasonableness of his Demand, which I have obtained leave to Insert.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="lat">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Domine <hi>Russel,</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>HƲ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Tabellario, quem non ita Pridem, ut alunt, Scripsisti Libelulum, &amp; nomen Fecisti <hi>Fidele Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>onium</hi> ad me dare ne graveris; in quo tu, ut Fama est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ihi Librum, <hi>Examen, &amp;c.</hi> dictum imputas; atque eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> me Sycophantiarum &amp; Mendaciorum reum peragis: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aque nihil iniquum postulo, quo melius liceat causam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cere.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Ex Domo Paterna oppido <hi>Darking</hi> Prid. No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>as <date>Aprilis.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:206806:4"/>
            <p>After the <hi>Doctor</hi> had viewed this a little, he began to fold it, and seem'd by his Posture to be going from the <hi>Bearer</hi> without so much as a Word of the Concern, <hi>who</hi> then thought it high time to inform him of what by all the Circumstances and Observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he made, supposed he was Ignorant of, <hi>viz.</hi> That an Answer was expected from him. This as he relates, put the Old Mortified Man into a violent Heat, and sent an Answer as like that of a Distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and confused Brain, as if it were hatch'd in his own; 1. That he knew not any use the Letter was of, unless to wipe his Backside. A Grave Answer for a Divine, and a <hi>Cambridge</hi> Doctor. Had the Bearer cry'd hold Sir, beware of that, least you add Fuel to the Fire, who could have blamed him? 2ly. That Mr. — had best mind his own Business, lest he Repent. To what part of the Letter this refers, I profess Ignorance. Unless it was none of Mr. — Business to remove those scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous Reflections, and false Accusations so plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heaped upon him in that invidious <hi>Pamphlet.</hi> 3ly. That Mr. — was an Impertinent Scandalous Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. All these Answers are most notoriously Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, as well as Uncivil; and Diametrically oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site to his great Pretensions of Sanctity and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; <hi>Nam mihi quale ingenium habes, fuit judicio ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio tua.</hi> The Tongue is the Index of the Mind, the very Picture and Disposition of the Heart. To sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the <hi>Dr.</hi> to be really ignorant of the Letter, as he said; is but to excuse the Impertinence of his Answer, not at all the indecency and railery of it, which might well have been spared, and more to his Reputation; but who could have suspected his Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance after so many Bounces as we have had, of his <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ew, Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin.</hi> And to suppose he understood the Letter, will but aggravate the Case; then his Denyal evidently appears a Design to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:206806:4"/> as much as he could, the Person vindicating his Reputation, from the Slurs with which his filthy Pamphlet endeavours to stain it.</p>
            <p>I hope Reader, you'l excuse for intruding so long on your Patience with these Passages; I have not done it to detain you from the matter in hand, nor to expose the Ignorance of the Doctor, so much as to inform you of the Temper and Disposition of his Spirit; an everlasting Argument of his Insincerity and meer Pretences to Mortification and Holiness.</p>
            <p>I proceed now to examine the <hi>trif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing Falshood and Disingenuity</hi> of the <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> called the <hi>Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thful Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Church of Christ, meeting at</hi> High-hall, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Crimes cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ged upon their Minister</hi> Doctor Russel.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Title</hi> had been passed without any Remarks, but that I was willing to correct a palpable Error, committed either by the <hi>Author</hi> or the <hi>Printer</hi> in the word <hi>Faithful,</hi> which is made one word, whereas it ought to be two distinct Words, with the Expletive Particle [of] between them, to be read thus; The <hi>Testimony full of Faith,</hi> &amp;c. For who knows not, that a very great degree is requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at this time of day, when all the World sets up for <hi>Virtuoso's,</hi> and fain wou'd be thought acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>cum tota rerum natura,</hi> both Moral and Divine; to pretend to set upon so impossible a Work, as to wash a filthy Black-moor white: Or prescribe a Dose which neither in <hi>quantity</hi> nor <hi>quality,</hi> is <hi>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="8 letters">
                     <desc>〈8 letters〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to have <hi>the least Operation,</hi> when by the <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of the <hi>Distemper</hi> the <hi>wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le Mass is Corrupted;</hi> but such <hi>Physicians</hi> (to say the best of them) must be only b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oy'd up with hopes of Miracles, being sensible of their Patients <hi>deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lity</hi> to bear the <hi>Op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> of a <hi>more powerful</hi> and <hi>proper Medicine.</hi> Instead of a <hi>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rry A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>te,</hi> called a <hi>Faithful Testimony,</hi> the <hi>Writ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natum</hi> or a publick Tryal before Impartial Judge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:206806:5"/> would have search'd to the quick, and convinced more, that they sincerely and heartily desired to make a perfect Cure; then a thousand <hi>Cabals</hi> at their <hi>Colledge</hi> at <hi>High-hall;</hi> or their Testimony's from thence of their faithful endeavours.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the Title, for I shall say nothing here of those Schismaticks, who call themselves the Church of Christ at▪ <hi>High-hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They begin their <hi>Tale</hi> with a hideous out-cry of a <hi>Scandalous Libel,</hi> called an <hi>Examen,</hi> &amp;c. which they say, contains several grievious Reflections on their beloved Brother, Pastor, and Messenger, Dr. <hi>William Russel,</hi> and charges him with very Gross and Abominable Immoralities. Thus they raise the Readers expectation to have a faithful Account of Horrible Matters acted against their beloved Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by some Wicked and Malicious <hi>Libeller;</hi> the like of which was never heard of before: But hold, he's basely deceived all on a suddain; for they only tell him, <hi>they are the same things the General Assembly, meeting at Goswel-street, had Charged upon him,</hi> 1698. <hi>in a Scandalous Paper, Signed by Three of their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come <hi>Reader,</hi> now you have it from their own Mouths, that the Things charged upon Dr. <hi>Russel</hi> in the <hi>Examen</hi> are the same, that the <hi>General Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> had Charged him with before. Consider there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>General Assembly</hi> is a great Body of <hi>Religious</hi> and <hi>Judicious</hi> Men, who we cannot think would take such grievous things upon slight Report; but be well assured of the Truth of them e're they gave them Credit; and to be sure they would never Exhibit <hi>them</hi> positively against him, as things he ought to be dealt with for, and so not only blast his Name, but expose themselves, and the Reputation of Religion; unless they thought themselves able to make them good by Credible and sufficient Witnesses.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:206806:5"/>
            <p>The <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Examen</hi> can't but be pleased sure with the Company the <hi>Dr.</hi> and his <hi>Friends</hi> have allowed him, to help support the Burthen they have cast upon his Shoulders, and consequently up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theirs, nay sometimes upon both without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction; <q>as Scandalous Libellers, whose Tongues and Pens are set on fire of Hell. Caffinite Malice; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments of Satan; Promoters and Propagaters of wicked Heresy; Abettors and Ʋpholders of Heretical, Blasphemous, and Damnable Opinions; want of Truth and Evidence, vile Aspersions;</q> with abundance more: Demonstrations that they themselves were pregnant with Rage, Malice and Calumnies, who could vent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d throw out so much in so little Room.</p>
            <p>But I suppose our <hi>Brethren</hi> of the <hi>General Assembly,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen they come to be acquainted with these Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, will think themselves obliged to Vindicate their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tegrity; and let the World know how basely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey are abused; that the Saddle may be laid on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght Horse; those vile Persons detected, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ested against; whose wicked and dishonourable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tions, till then, are, and will be prejudicial to our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oly Profession.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, if the <hi>Authors</hi> of the <hi>Faithful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>estimony</hi> please, I'le shew them their own <hi>Pictures,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Doctors Glass:</hi>
               <q>It represents to 'em the frame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f their Spirits by the Rage and Scurrility of their Tongues and Pens; 'tis in vain for them to think they are better for <hi>Scisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vindicat. of the Babt. Church. p. 9.</note> while such Corrupt <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications</hi> proceed out of their Mouths; Indications of Corrupt and <hi>unmortified Hearts;</hi> for out of the abundance of the Heart the Mouth speaketh: Revilings are contrary to all those Exhortations in the Gospel; as Meekness, Kindness, Tenderness, and Charity. Our Lord a Prince of Peace; His Gospel, a Gospel of Peace;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:206806:6"/> His People Peacable, Gentle, and easie to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated; hath himself set us a blessed Example, not to Revile tho' Reviled; nor Threaten tho' we Suffer; but commit your selves to him that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Righteously:</q> And then he draws all its Rays to a point, that implies, unless you are thus quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ye cannot expect a Blessing in your Deed: So that if your Faithful Testimony meets not with that Credit you expected; your beloved Brother says, 'tis because you are not Meek, Tender, Charitable, and in a word, not Mortified.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Contrivers</hi> of the <hi>Faithful Testimony,</hi> in divers places of it, make a great noise, because the <hi>Examen</hi> is <hi>Anonymous:</hi> From thence they would insinuate, it is a False and Malicious Thing; that the Author was ashamed and afraid to own it; as much as to say, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less he be so Ambitious of being known as the <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tor,</hi> and puts his Name to every thing he Writes, it is not to be credited; but this it seems hath prevailed with many, and been prejudicial to its Authority; not surely with any, but the byassed and the blind, who can't, or will not see better. Themselves (you hear) tell us, the Crimes it chargeth upon the Doctor, are the same that were <hi>Exhibited</hi> against <hi>him</hi> in a <hi>Paper</hi> by the <hi>General Assembly,</hi> which Paper is inserted in the <hi>Examen, p.</hi> 13. and Subscribed in the Name and by the order of the <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly,</hi> by <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. Amory,</hi> and <hi>Tho. Bowes;</hi> Which one would think the Intelligent and Impartial should E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r more Anthentick then the Authors Name, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m be who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he will; so that this Objection must needs appear to wise Men, only a Cavil to extenuate the Authority of the Book; especially since they pretend certain knowledge of the Author.</p>
            <p>Af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er we are informed in the first Page, that the <hi>Exam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> contains only some old scandalous Matters formerly charged by the <hi>Ass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbly.</hi> In the Second,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:206806:6"/> we have an obscure and deceitful account of a full and serious Examination, in the Year 1698. Of all those things the Doctor was accused off: We are told they appointed a Church Meeting, to hear and Examine the Charges, wherein they had the Assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <hi>divers Teachers</hi> and <hi>Principal Brethren</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> at <hi>Whites-Alley;</hi> and also of Mr. <hi>Ben. Morley,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Fran. Morrice;</hi> that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded at that time (as a Church) to hear, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine all those things th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir <hi>Brother</hi> was Charged with; and upon a full and serious Examina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it did appear to them, the Proof Alledged was not sufficient to prove him <hi>Guilty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now by this Formal and Specious Account, I presume, no Man alive cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d imagine, they had neither the Accusers nor their Witnesses before them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o, not so much as One of them; but it is very true, and yet their Consciences can serve to insinuate they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad heard and examined at that time, the Accusers and Witnesses themselves, of all that could be Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected against the <hi>Doctor,</hi> and so impose a Lye upon the World: What abominable Deceit is here! <hi>These</hi> are they which pretend to <hi>Religion;</hi> but well thought on, 'tis that of <hi>High-hall:</hi> These are the <hi>Doctors Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rgators,</hi> and who by licking their beloved Brother, proclaim their own Insincerity to the World, and the <hi>Falshood</hi> of their <hi>Faithful-Testimony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But suppose they had heard what the Proof was, or the <hi>Doctor</hi> acquainted them, who was no <hi>Ignora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> in that Matter; and considered of its validity, why did they not tell us so, instead of deceiving us with Words, and endeavouring to make us believe they had the Witnesses before 'em? And why pray did they not acquaint us wherein the proof Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged was insufficient to prove him Guilty; this indeed would have had some appearance in it. Ay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut those things were not to be known by us, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:206806:7"/> was their Sense on't; we must take it on their Word; believe as the Church believes; or we had the amends in our own Hands; for to question their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of Judging, is grand Presumption, their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiality a breach of <hi>Charity;</hi> and deserve an <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema:</hi> And to contradict them to be sure is a <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Heresy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let none think it strange I charge these Gentlemen with an unparalel'd stock of Confidence; for all the World must allow it too, when, besides what I have Noted already, they are informed, that a great many of the Things have been proved upon him long since, and he dealt with, and confest, and pretended Humiliation for 'em.</p>
            <p>But what do they mean by being manifest from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable Evidence, that the things cannot possibly be true, that the Prime or First Evidence knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of them. In the former things they tell us the Proof was not sufficient; here they rise a degree higher, and positively deny there was any thing in it: Next perhaps, they may aver, he was never Charged with such Things; what say the <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> you I mean, that are so credulous, you'l believe 'em will ye not?</p>
            <p>Once more, what do they mean? The <hi>Doctor</hi> was accused of picking up a Miss of the Town; of being Drunk; and taken in her Company, all which is Recorded in Sr. <hi>Edward Clarks</hi> Book: And yet they say, they are impossible, by undenyable Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; and that the Persons from whom the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses (Accusars they should have said) pretend to spake them, deny they spoke them, or knew any thing of 'em. Well, and what can we say now? that Things so plain and Evident are deny'd, Recorded in a Magistrates Journal, Deposited upon Oath, for which the <hi>Doctor</hi> was Fined, and paid Five Shillings for being Drunk, and the Woman committed to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:206806:7"/> Goal, why only thus much, that they are Persons of unheard of Confidence, so far from <hi>Religion,</hi> that they have no Regard to Truth, their own Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Common Honesty; and if people are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent so to be imposed upon, e'n let 'em for the future.</p>
            <p>I Remember indeed, one Mr. <hi>Hore</hi> was very Officious in this Matter, and he reported it seem'd to him impossible the <hi>Doctor</hi> should be drunk, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dering the time of his going from Home, upon the Word of the <hi>Doctor;</hi> for that to be sure must come from Him or <hi>His;</hi> and from the Account he received at the <hi>George</hi> and <hi>Vulture,</hi> where it was ungrounded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reported, by some that the <hi>Doctor</hi> and his <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ress</hi> had been Drinking: But I never heard till <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow, it was impossible the <hi>Doctor</hi> should be taken in Company of the <hi>Woman,</hi> and had befor Sr. <hi>Edward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ark;</hi> this is a <hi>Degree</hi> before that <hi>Gentleman,</hi> and yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Man of very great Assurance; who will not hesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate to say, with as grave a look as usually grac'd withall, that Drunkenness and Whoring are Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es to the Opinion of <hi>Caffin;</hi> nor stick to deny that ever he said it; the very next breath, with a blush, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>othing unusual to a Man of his Modesty; nor to affirm it again as Company invites or provokes him; and yet this Gentleman is one off, if not the only Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible Testimony.</p>
            <p>But to return, if these things are so impossible as they pretend, and the real Witness deny to know any thing of them; whence is it I pray the <hi>Doctor</hi> and his Friends are unwilling to come to a publick Tryal? This is very unaccountable to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>idering Men, and must needs be a greater prejudice to his Cause then ever they'l be able to retrieve: An Innocent Man need never fear; if that don't always secure him from the Rage and Design of Wicked and Malicious Men; it must certainly administer
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:206806:8"/> Peace to his Conscience which will support him under all Tryals.</p>
            <p>Perhaps it may be enquired here, if the Things are so plain as we make for, why did not we appear and make them Good at their invitations. I answer, first their Meetings were appointed by order of the Church as they Call themselves; they tell us they proceeded as a Church: Now they well knew the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons concerned would not own them for a <hi>Church</hi> unless <hi>Schismaticks</hi> may be called so; And that to appear at their invitation would be to grant them a Church, the Author of the <hi>Examen</hi> produces the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors own Words, namely, that <hi>he would not agree the Church at</hi> White's Alley <hi>should appoint Persons to Confer with those that left 'em; because that would be to own 'em a Church:</hi> So that if this be not a sufficient Reason 'tis the Doctors, and therefore obligeth him to mete with his own Bushel. Then all the Persons who were to be Judges in the Case were of their own Choosing; and such as were not proper: tho' I will not affirm of them, <hi>Reddent vicem si reposcatur.</hi> Lastly their Meetings were at Times and Places of their own appointing; and therefore that Freedom and Liberty could not be expected; nor the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of so many Persons, as were absolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary in the Case.</p>
            <p>These are the Reasons I presume; wherefore no Body accepted their Invitations; and these they were acquainted with by Persons offended, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after the First Meeting; and long before the Second by the Author of the <hi>Examen;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to resolve upon the same Measures this last time, they were assured of beforehand would not be satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory to offended <hi>Persons,</hi> was plainly to tell us, they were so far from obliging us with a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and impartial Hearing that now they bid us de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance and absolutely determined to shelter the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:206806:8"/> and stifle the Matters against him as much as they could.</p>
            <p>So much for the Delivering of <hi>Adonis,</hi> whose <hi>Chastity</hi> at last, having been often charged to be smitten and entangled with the Charms of <hi>Venus,</hi> is wonderfully vindicated both by the <hi>Conjunction of Impossible Circumstances</hi> and the <hi>Insufficiency</hi> of Mr. <hi>Hearsay,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Know-nothings Testimony,</hi> from the Rage and Malice of <hi>Satan's Instruments</hi> set forth in a Wicked <hi>Scandalous Libel</hi> Contrived, Written and Published by no body knows who.</p>
            <p>Next in particular comes on the Tryal and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of Mr. <hi>Bacchus,</hi> a Great Crony of the Ladys, a very fit Companion, (<hi>sinecerere &amp;</hi> Baccho <hi>friget</hi> Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus) Look yonder he comes Do but behold the Beast. —There from the <hi>Sark-house,</hi> along by the <hi>Zythopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists</hi> Doors. Ha! What a Steering I'l warrant ye to <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob's</hi> Well, to allay the <hi>Nectar</hi> and Qualify himself for the <hi>Theater</hi> to Morrow. How he Swags, Nay he Bows like a Bulrush. Now, now, to the Lady! Mad—am, your Um—ble Ser—Ser—vant. See, see he's down. Well there let him lie, And come on Sir, let us hear how he's acquitted.</p>
            <p>As touching the Doctors falling down in the Street which gave rise, they say, to the Report of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Drunk, divers there present, declare he had been many times troubled with Fits, which some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times seized him with great Violence.</p>
            <p>What a pretty sham Story is here! Mark it, he fell down in the Street and that gave rise to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port he was Drunk. No Gentlemen, that some of you might have done. He did not only fall down, but continued down, and at last was sent home in a <hi>Coach,</hi> where some of his Friends were, who have confest he was Drunk, and smell'd so strong of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors they were not able to assist him, nor car'd to stay for the Shame and Scandal of it. Moreover,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:206806:9"/> this action was so far from giving the rise to it, that he can be proved an habitual Drunkard long before.</p>
            <p>But suppose he hath been troubled with Fits, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides Mad Drunken ones, what then? It does not follow from thence, that this was one; which was the thing they ought have given Satisfaction in, and therefore had it been a Fit, why did they not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce some Persons among those many that saw him to testify it? This was very requisite and would have carried something of a Face with it; were they credible and the Circumstances agreeing: but they pretend to nothing of this Nature; and yet unanimously agree that they consciously believe it, <hi>IT!</hi> What? Why that this falling down was from the Distemper of his Head, and not Drinking: to which Mr. <hi>Morley,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Morris</hi> subscribe their Names together with the Congregation, as their Judgment of the whole business.</p>
            <p>Now this is the whole Conclusion of the first Meeting, which relates only to the latter Thing, namely, his being Drunk, when he fell down; so that the Contriver of the <hi>Faithful Testimony</hi> shews his Cunning and Deceit, in making a great Noise of a full and serious Examination of all Things their Brother was charged with, the Proof whereof appeared insufficient; and of the Impossibility of the Things about the Constable, together with the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses Ignorance, and Denyal of their knowing any thing of them; and then in omiting all in the Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and Determination of the Church; And all this is so jumbled together, that an undiscerning Person cannot well discover the Juggle.</p>
            <p>So that there is no such Thing to be found in the Resolution of this first Meeting; that upon a full and serious Examination, all the Matters alledg'd against him, were not Sufficient to prove him Guilty, yet they insinuate this in the whole Account, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:206806:9"/> in these Words, And because they are the same old Stores, recited in the <hi>Examen,</hi> we thought to have past it by in Silence, &amp;c. And in <hi>p.</hi> 3. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, We had heard the Matters charged against him, and acquitted therefrom long since, yet we did agree to consider 'em again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Reason of this Omission seems to be. The Persons who examined the Matter were too sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of the Truth and Evidence of 'em, so much as to give it under their Hands, that they really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved he was not Guilty; but chose rather to sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle out this Crime, which they flatter'd themselves was the lattest, and most difficult to be Proved; and therefore the fitest for their Design to maintain him in his Schism, and impose on such as knew no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; for it can't be thought, had they quitted him of those Matters, the <hi>Doctor</hi> and his Friends would have been guilty of so great an over sight. But this they endeavour to make amends for in their second Meeting by denying all in the Bulk, tho' on no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ground than the former.</p>
            <p>And 'twill be well for a bad Cause if this general and Partial Information hath been the only Snare to Mr. <hi>Steed,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sharp,</hi> in being so far concerned in the Faithful Testimony, as I find they are and come now to enquire into.</p>
            <p>But by the Way, It is a Matter of no small Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how the <hi>Doctor</hi> procured these two <hi>Calvinistical Antimonians</hi> to be his Vouchers; for 'tis within the Memory of a Man, the <hi>Doctor</hi> affirm'd that <hi>Calvinism</hi> was a great deal worse than <hi>Caffinism,</hi> which yet Mr. <hi>Hore</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jac.</hi> pronounce worse than the greatest Immoralities; and all of them Blasphemous, Heretical, Idolatrous and Damnable. At another, if not at the same time he advised one, who asked his Opinion in the Case, to joyn with the old Assembly; for he had Thoughts too of doing it himself. But
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:206806:10"/> now that he dissembled in both these, especially his Cast at <hi>Calvinism,</hi> and consequently was in a fit, i. e. a fit of Hypocrisy, can be no question, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the exact conformity there is betwixt their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and his Practice; which is far from Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencing good Works necessary to Salvation. And hence indeed, it is not so great a Wonder, he made Choice of these Men, who utterly Cashier the Law of God, and consequently destroy the Distinction, the Legalist, as they call 'em, make betwixt Virtue and Vice.</p>
            <p>These <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> p. 6. 7. tell us <hi>they thought it their Concernment to use the best means they could in Righteousness for information in the Truth of these Things. i. e: Charged on the</hi> Doctor <hi>in the</hi> Examen; <hi>and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were desirous to be Present, when those Accusations might be fairly heard; knowing it would be unjust to judge of a Matter on Reports, till they had obtained opportunity to hear the Charge opened, Testimony and Evidences ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, and the whole Affair Candidly Debated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no doubt to be made sure, but that these <hi>Gentlemen</hi> who have thus introduced us with the just Methods, <hi>Persons</hi> Righteously and Sincerely enclined, are obliged to take to <hi>Judge</hi> of Matters of so much Moment, and which chiefly concern the <hi>Reputation</hi> of their most Holy <hi>Profession,</hi> have very well acquitted themselves in all these Respects.</p>
            <p>But however considering they are but Men, and <hi>Humanum est errare,</hi> we will not pass without exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining into their managment; and if found to devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate from so just a Rule, I shall not spare to Discipline them with their own <hi>Virgâ;</hi> and I am sure Judicious <hi>Christians,</hi> who are truly Zealous for <hi>Gods</hi> Cause, will not blame me, when they consider how very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial it is for <hi>Persons</hi> in such Eminent Stations to <hi>Err,</hi> not to say play the <hi>Hypocrite</hi> in so <hi>Solemn</hi> a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:206806:10"/>
            <p>Now as a part of the best means these <hi>Gentlemen</hi> could <hi>use</hi> in <hi>Righteousness</hi> for <hi>Information,</hi> which they say, was their Concernment, and pretend to have used; they were obliged to take care, that the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons who had undertaken to prove the Things, should be acquainted with these several <hi>Postulata.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Timely Notice, and Invitation.</item>
               <item>2. Place.</item>
               <item>3. Judges of the Cause.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All these to be sure are absolutely necessary to be done by such as pretend to be Righteous Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</p>
            <p>Nay farther, they ought to acquaint themselves also, whether their Proposals were accepted; If not, for what reason Objected against; and to do their utmost Endeavour to remove them by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, son, if Unreasonable, or by Compliance, if not.</p>
            <p>If any of these Endeavours were wanting by these <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> unless impossible to be come at, they must needs act Repugnant to their own Consciences, by contradicting the Means they inform us was their Concern and absolutely necessary to qualifie them for Judges of the Matters.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Examen,</hi> they are acquainted with several Things, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That the Matters of Fact would be proved upon Mr. <hi>Russel,</hi> by the <hi>Members</hi> of several <hi>Congregations;</hi> dare <hi>He</hi> or his <hi>Friends,</hi> either <hi>Legally</hi> or before <hi>both Assemblies</hi> call and invite them to it: That a great part of the Things he had been Convicted of, and dealt with for, at <hi>Barbican;</hi> that he stood Accused of willful Lying at <hi>Goswel-street;</hi> and that as to the <hi>Business</hi> of the <hi>Constable</hi> it was Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in Sr. <hi>Edward Clarks</hi> Journals.</p>
            <p>We must suppose the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> acquainted with these things, and Consequently with the means of Information, because they tell us they had seen the <hi>Libel,</hi> meaning the <hi>Examen.</hi> So that they might
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:206806:11"/> have given, or caused to be given <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>Timely notice</hi> to those <hi>Members</hi> of divers <hi>Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> mentioned in the <hi>Examen,</hi> who undertook to prove the <hi>Charges;</hi> that at such a Time, and Place, and before such Persons, appointed to hear, and Determine of the Matters; they were expected to appear, and make good those things they charge on the <hi>Doctor;</hi> where they should have free Liberty and due Encouragement. And here they ought to have given substantial Reason why they refused to let the Cause be heard before both Assemblies; and why they took such Methods as they must needs suppose would not be accepted; that so they might have used all proper means to Justifie their Proceedings, and Convince People they designed not Partiality. They might have applyed themselves to <hi>Barbican</hi> and been acquainted of the Truth of those Matters; as well as to <hi>Goswel-street,</hi> concerning his willful Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing just before he Schismatized: They might also have gone or sent to Sr. <hi>Edward Clark,</hi> and Examined the Truth of that Matter, and seen he was Recorded for picking up the Woman; and being Drunk, with the Deposition; but all this they neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected; and yet pretend to make use of the best Means they could in Righteousness for Information in the Truth, being sensible how unjust it is to Judge of a Matter without hearing the Charge open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Testimony and Evidences Examined, and the whole Affair Candidly Debated.</p>
            <p>Nay, beyond all this, they immediately subjoyn; and accordingly (i. e. they mean according to these pretensions of their Sincere Endeavours, to search out the Truth) being admitted by the Church, to be present at that Season (<hi>viz.</hi> when by their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Charge ought to be opened, the Testimony and Evidences Examined, and the whole Matter Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly Debated before just Judgment could be given)
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:206806:11"/> they heard the Matter Impartially and Judiciously Presented, Considered and Determined, which at least plainly implies thus much; that the Charge was opened, the Testmony Examined, and the whole Candidly Debated, which is Horrible Wickedness, and a mocking the Great God, as well as deluding the World.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed, they do tell us after this, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Compiler</hi> nor his <hi>Abettors,</hi> were able to make the Things good; because he knew of the Meeting a Week before, and refused to come to it.</p>
            <p>But this, were it true, as it is not, would be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufficient to clear them from a Design of Imposing on the unwary Reader: For by the plain Sence and Connexion of the Words; no body can imagine that if neither the <hi>Compiler,</hi> nor <hi>Abettors</hi> were there, yet some of the <hi>Accusers</hi> were; because 'tis incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to think the Matters should be impartially repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented by any of the <hi>Doctors Friends;</hi> so much as to the satisfaction of these Gentlemen, who had but just before declared the unjustness of Judging upon <hi>Reports,</hi> and without hearing the Testimony and Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences Examined, and the Matter Candidly Debated.</p>
            <p>Besides their telling us they heard the Matter Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially presented, considered, and determined; and then immediatly adding these Words, <hi>viz.</hi> they do also declare as things appear to them by Evident and Authentick Testimony, <hi>Doctor Russel</hi> is not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of those Vile Enormities laid to his Charge, in that Scandalous Pamphlet, is an evident Distinction betwixt that Addition of theirs and the determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they just before tell you they came to, upon the Matters, being Impartially presented and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered: So that they stand on two different Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, and consequently it is Evident they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to insinuate, that their Determination of the whole Affair, together with the Church as you
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:206806:12"/> have it Page the 5th. where they are Represent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to agree with them, was founded upon the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Examination of the Evidences which they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate is absolutely necessary to make competent Judges: And that besides this they verily believe the <hi>Dr.</hi> is not guilty from Evident and Authentick Testimony, that was given in his behalf. To say this is not their Sence, is what I contend for, because it gives themselves the Lye, and acquaints the World with their Hypocrisy, who expresly tell us, that they knew it would be unjust to judge of a Matter on bare Report, till they heard the Charge opened, the Testimony and Evidences Examined, and the whole Affair Candidly Debated; and consequently that it was their Opinion no Testimony, in behalf of the accused Person is sufficient; but both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties must be heard, which they insinuate with all seeming sincerity imaginable, was their Design.</p>
            <p>I come now to observe what they say, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the supposed Author of the <hi>Examen,</hi> and to shew that those very measures they took, make against them; and is a farther Confirmation of their Deceit and Hypocrisy.</p>
            <p>Their Words are, and for him that was the Writer of it, to refuse his Appearance to shew Grounds, and Testimony for those grievous Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations; tho' he knew a Week before hand of their designed Meeting, and was invited and desired to come to it; did evidently declare that neither he, nor the Abettors were able to make any Truth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in those Vile Reproaches cast upon him in that Scurrilous Libel.</p>
            <p>By this Consequence of their own drawing, 'tis manifest the Persons knowledge of their Meeting and Invitation to it were antecedently necessary to his appearance; because they make that the formal cause of it, <hi>i. e.</hi> of their conclusion or consequence;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:206806:12"/> that he nor the Abe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttors were able to make good the things.</p>
            <p>And as they suppose these things necessary, they must also suppose certainty as to the Person, and that it was his business to appear, as well as a suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time to do it in, with his Evidence; if any of these be wanting their Inferrence is altogether Falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious; for as he Could not do it without Knowledge and Admittance; he could not without timely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, nor obliged unless really the Person that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook it, especially if they are directed to the undertakers. Now the Mischief on't is, their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is subject to all these Disadvantages, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently is a perfect Fallacy, which will appear by enquiring into the Matters.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the supposed Author, as he tells me, did acknowledge he had heard of their Meeting about Four or Five Days or a Week before: But what then? It is as true he knew not of their Design, but was inquisitive of the Measures they intended to take; for he had heard of the Matter, and Thought it was Expedient such Things should be sifted out, and the Blame and Scandal be laid on the Backs of those who deserve it; for the Prejudice of Religion was never greater, nor the Causes more connived at, then in in this present Age; so that they have nothing to Boast of on that account; for what did it signify to know of their Meeting, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Design; nor that he might be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>As for the Invitation they talk of, when was that? How long before the Meeting? why they tell you in their Faithful Testimony four Hours, indeed! What Four Hours? A huge long time! surely the Gentlemen could not think this enough. Yes they did; Nay and they do not only bring it in thus, He pretended the Notice was too short, tho he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:206806:13"/> with it FOUR HOURS before the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but concluded from it too; that he had no real Excuse for his Absence but want of Truth and Evidence; Truly I think the Person acted very dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly to refuse to make his Appearance before such unreasonable Creatures. And I Appeal now in his behalf, whether Four Hours Warning was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together Irrational, pray Consider they had no Assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of finding him at Home; but if they did acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally, can it be thought he could have the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of so many Witnesses at an Hours Warning, or two; besides I know it impossible to do them all Word in that time, And therefore if they really suspected him to be the Author as they Insinuate in more Places then one, when the Meeting was first appointed, 'tis Evident they design'd to Trick and Surprise him, and to make that a Pretence, but was in reality a Contrivance to shelter the <hi>Dr.</hi> from Justice: and if they did not suspect him, then 'tis as plain, they had no Thoughts of a Publick and Impartial Tryal; and yet these Men as you have often heard, pretend that was their Design: So that let it be which way it will, they were far from doing all they could in Righteousness for Information; or giving the Reader a faithful Testimony of what they did.</p>
            <p>But suppose this Person had been invited in time, they had no Reason nor Grounds to make the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement they do of his refusing to come, unless certain he was the Author: For else he could not be obliged; nor their Cause receive Advantage. But he did not deny it they say, What then; Are there no Prudential Reasons to be given for this? Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose he was a Friend to the Cause, and acquainted with what the Author says in the last Leaf of the Preface to the <hi>Examen, viz.</hi> that he was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the Controversy; but referr'd to those that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:206806:13"/> were and would undertake it; 'twas his Prudence to put a stop to any farther Enquiry about him; For he might easily Scent the Intriegue, which evidently appeared in their enquiring after the Author, who had assured them the Cause was none of his; and supprest his Name, an Evidence he would be no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concern'd in it; and at the same time wholly neglect the Means directed to, of finding out those Members of several Congregations, who promised to appear and prove the Matters upon him.</p>
            <p>Lastly, Suppose he was the Author, yet seeing he assured them the Cause was not his, and concealed his Name on that very Account. But withal ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted 'em of the Persons whose Business it was, and had undertook and promised to defend it, on publick Notice, and proper Conditions; he is no farther Concerned, nor to be esteemed than a Representer of the Matter, in order to a publick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earing.</p>
            <p>Thus Reader you see the Great noise and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement made of sending to the Author, and his denying to Come is vanished into Smoak: So that for them to conclude he absented for want of Truth, is a meer <hi>non sequitur,</hi> and Involves their Cause into Design and Intriegue.</p>
            <p>You have heard he had not timely Notice; nor they Assurance he was the Author, nor he sufficient Reason to appear, when he had informed them, 'twas to Business of his immediately, and intimated he would be no farther concerned; but directed to those that would; For them therefore to fix upon him, nay upon him only under these Considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is a Demonstration they did all they could to stifle the Matter, and Conceal the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness.</p>
            <p>And this will be more abundantly confirmed by Considering the Answer the supposed Author return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:206806:14"/>
'em by M. <hi>Jenkins</hi> their <hi>Messenger.</hi> He told me he objected against the Place, Time, and Persons: The First he says was not Convenient; The Second not Sufficient; The Third not Proper. Had he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of their Measures, or it been proper to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of them, he had heard of their Meetings, (as he told Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi>) about a Week before. What Ingenious Persons are these now, that can turn this to their Advantage, and make a noise of a Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Cconcession! But what follows! He ordered Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> to tell the <hi>Docter</hi> and his <hi>Friends;</hi> that whether he was the Author or not; yet if they would submit their Cause to be hear'd as the <hi>Exame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> requires, <hi>viz.</hi> before both the <hi>Assemblies,</hi> he'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to produce sufficient Witness to prove the Things, it Charges on the <hi>Doctor,</hi> upon timely notice. But all this would not do, it signified not a Rush; they proceed notwithstanding: So Just were these <hi>Judges;</hi> and so sincerely disposed to use the best means they could in Righteousness for Information. These one would think, were perfectly the Actions of Madmen, or those at least that have no sensible Love of Religion, nor tender Concern for their own Reputation.</p>
            <p>Well, as I said, they Proceed notwithstanding and draw up their Resolutions, and Judgment of the whole.</p>
            <p>That as Matters do now appear to the Church and to the rest here present on the most diligent and strict enquiry we could make, our Beloved <hi>Brother Russel</hi> is not guilty of these Crimes, or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moralities charged on him in the aforesaid Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet.</p>
            <p>That is to say; he is not guilty of offering that incivility it relates to the <hi>Gentlewoman</hi> at <hi>High-gate;</hi> tho' she is still alive and others that saw it, who will attest the Truth of it, when duly called: No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:206806:14"/> Guilty of the Immodest Action to the <hi>Gentlewoman</hi> in <hi>Moorfields;</hi> not to her in <hi>Cloath-Fair;</hi> not guilty of picking up another Mans Wife in the Street, and making satisfaction for it; nor of being left in a <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern</hi> by a <hi>Gilt,</hi> chous'd of his Money, and pretending to be <hi>Justice Ʋnderhill;</hi> not of being Drunk several times, and seen by some that have, and by others that will attest it when required; not of being brought Drunk before a <hi>Justice</hi> of the <hi>Peace,</hi> whom I forbear to mention; in short (to repeat no more of the Things) He is not guilty they say, of being tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in Company of a <hi>Common Woman,</hi> and had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sr. <hi>Edward Clark,</hi> and of being drunk as depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sited upon Oath; and consequently too, they say, he has not been Convicted of any of these Things at <hi>Barbican,</hi> nor dealt with for them. And all this without coming to a publick Hearing; nay refusing to do it, notwithstanding they have been so publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dared to it, and more especially by the sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed Author, when they were just met to hear and determine the Matter by the best means they could use in Righteousness for Information; knowing it unjust to Judge of a Matter without hearing the Charge opened, the Testimony and Evidences exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and the whole Affair Candidly Debated.</p>
            <p>So that there is an absolute necessity to conclude; that either these <hi>two Gentlemen</hi> were imposed upon; or else have acted Repugnant to those Methods, they simulate sincerely to propose before God and all the World, was their Concern and Design; and consequently contrary to their Consciences; but this (I hope) I may say for them, they would not wilfully do; and therefore conclude they have been trick'd by the <hi>Doctor.</hi> However it will be a blot in their Eschutcheon, so long as they continue to shelter him from a Publick and Impartial Tryal.</p>
            <p>But these Gentlemen tell us, <hi>page</hi> the 6th. that they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:206806:15"/> are greatly grieved such things should be alledg'd against the <hi>Doctor,</hi> who had publickly with Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration and sound Argument been enabled to defend, the despised way of Christ.</p>
            <p>This puts me in mind of what Dr. <hi>Jackson</hi> said to the supposed Author, (as he tells me) and perhaps they are partly of a mind: He said tho' he would not justifie the <hi>Doctor</hi> concerning the Crimes charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon him, yet he would Apologize in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, as a worthy Instrument to defend the Cause of <hi>God.</hi> At another time he affirm'd that <hi>Drunkeness</hi> and <hi>Whoring</hi> were <hi>Vertues</hi> to <hi>Socinianism, Arianism</hi> and <hi>Caffinism;</hi> and that <hi>Robert Hore</hi> was nothing to blame, but in receding from it, and further that were all true charged on the <hi>Doctor,</hi> yet as before, he was deservedly worthy of a good Name in the World. To what a strange pitch of Confidence are these Gentlemen arriv'd? But some Men are very Charitable to their Neighbours about Immoralities, and Sins of the deepest dye; but can't exercise a Grain in Matters of <hi>Religion;</hi> the first perhaps from the instance of the <hi>Adultress,</hi> whom our <hi>Saviour</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded first of all to be Ston'd by the Innocent; the second as likely, because they cannot away with to be contradicted, and hold it as great presumption, nay, as damnable a Sin, to call their Vain and Empty Dictates into question, as the best Pope of 'em all; but notwithstanding, the People to whom they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, if to any body; for I think a Stranger may well make that a question, will call 'em to an Account, and make 'em examples, for giving their disrespect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and irreligious Tongues such a liberty, to call those certain and indubitable Matters into question, <hi>Chastity</hi> and <hi>Temperance,</hi> in which all the <hi>Christian,</hi> World is agreed, nay, the very Deists themselves, and make 'em more uncertainly determin'd by the Scripture, than these profound Mysteries that have
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:206806:15"/> been Bon's of Contention in all Ages; and Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized by some Men as <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>Good</hi> as any since the <hi>Apostles</hi> Days. They could not more sliely, I think, have suggested their own <hi>Infidelity</hi> and contempt of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> I have heard before now indeed the <hi>Character</hi> of some <hi>Gentlemen</hi> Desplayed, and I fear 'tis too true of 'em; which I'll give you, and those the free Liberty of claiming it, who think they best de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve it; 'Tis said, they have so much of the <hi>Notion</hi> and <hi>Theory</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> as to be able to <hi>Harangue</hi> and <hi>Chatt</hi> it over a Pot of <hi>Ale,</hi> a Dish of <hi>Coffee,</hi> or a Glass of <hi>Canary,</hi> Day after Day, from one Weeks end to another, with as much <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Ostentation</hi> as most Men alive; And that they have just Wit enough to <hi>Banter</hi> and <hi>Ridicule</hi> in a peculiar Way, the most sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and Pious Persons, serious and weighty Matters, that don't suit their Gusts. They are for Governing every Body, but Directing and Instructing no Body, either with Spiritual Gifts amongst their Brethren; or with <hi>Example</hi> and <hi>Savour</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Conversations. So that for the Practical Part and Profession of Religion, I dont hear they have any more than some of none of the best of their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. But to return,</p>
            <p>Surely these <hi>Gentlemen</hi> must take the Cause of the <hi>Antipaedobaptists</hi> to be desperate, to pretend need of such a Defender as the <hi>Doctor.</hi> And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>efore let him be as able as he will, I cannot Apprehend that such a Scandalous Person is fit to be employed in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending Religion, who is so far from living it, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by a Body of People. Nay I don't conceive how they can be Just to their Profession to admit him. If Mr. <hi>Jack.</hi> does <hi>Apologize,</hi> 'tis ten to one but some Body will have somewhat or another to say to it.</p>
            <p>In the mean time I think it is sufficient if such a Man, tho' truly sensible of his Wickedness be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusted with the smalest Talent, I mean the very
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:206806:16"/> meanest Place in the Church, tho' for Parts and Ability we should suppose him qualified for the most Honourable: But the many Steps he hath made of late, exclusive of these Crimes, to advance, and get himself a Name, is an Evidence to me, he swells with Ostentation and is no more fit for a Church than the Pulpet.</p>
            <p>I Remember it hath been an old Story, nay still in the Mouth of some People, that the <hi>Doctor</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally reformed and become a new Creature, both in the <hi>Church</hi> and in his <hi>Family:</hi> Of this Mind are seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, but amongst them all, I shall only mention Mr. <hi>Jo. Jenkins,</hi> he having lately given this as his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, it is the more Pertinent to our Purpose. When he was with the supposed Author, who reflected on him for Partiality, supposing he had been Zealous with others to Eject Mr. <hi>J. T.</hi> whose Case he sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed came short of the <hi>Doctors,</hi> seeing he fell under the Charges; tho long First, which was some small formal sort of Expiation, but the <hi>Doctor</hi> continued to deny the Things charged upon him; so deceived abundance of People, especially his own Hearers, and his own Soul too, which made him the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Scandal to Religion, and was an Aggravation of of his Sin. To this Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> in substance replied, that he Charged him falsely: For the <hi>Doctors</hi> Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were acquainted of the former Things, and that the <hi>Doctor</hi> had been humbled, and had made Satisfaction for them. And as for the Truth of what he affirmed, was so Pert and Cock-sure as to challenge the Person to make his Assertion Good. And a little before this the Person alleding the Notice was too short to procure so many Witnesses as that Case required. No replied Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> that can be no Excuse; Talk of a Great many Witnesses, (Apostrophically) need of a great many Witnesses to prove the Business of Sir <hi>Edward Cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k,</hi> or any thing else since he was an <hi>Elder;</hi> for the old Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:206806:16"/> they require nothing, expressing himself, as tho' they were well enough satisfied about them; the very Words the Person hath forgotten, but is sure this is the Sense of them. And therefore call'd on Mr <hi>Jackson</hi> to take notice, the Gentleman allow'd the former Matters, and required only that of Sir <hi>Edward Clark</hi> to be proved. Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> must not be thought so unfaithful to his Friend, volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily to give away so much of his Cause; but that he had good Grounds for what he said, and conceived it a vain Thing for the <hi>Doctor,</hi> or his Friends to go about to deny them. And indeed his very mentioning the old Matters in such a manner, must needs suggest the <hi>Doctors</hi> Reformation. It has been the Common Vogue among the Doctor's best Friends ever since the <hi>Sabbatarian</hi> Book came out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, that he was a reformed Man; and therefore the Author shew'd a malicious Spirit to reap up such old Stories, and for which he hath given Satisfaction long since. And I can tell you, that then a Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Gentleman was of the same Opinion, with some others, not so innocent as they ought to be, who contradicts it now by subscribing their Testimony, and so proclaim themselves Men of Untruth in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me now demand of these Gentlemen that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be sensible of his Reformation, and enda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to make it others Satisfaction, as well as that they have made it their own, in what Actions of his Life hath it been manifested: They say a Thing cannot be, and not appear. Let us therefore know wherein his Reformation is apparent? Is it in often contracting those vile Actions charged upon him, and never sincerely repenting of them; or in his sometimes pretended Repentance, but more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Repetition, for little less than the Space of Thirty Years together, as can be proved upon him.</p>
            <p>But more Especially Gentlemen I am extream ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest to know whether you continue your Opinion of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:206806:17"/> his Reformation from the Grounds he gave the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribers of the <hi>Testimony,</hi> to conclude and agree with one Consent, p. 5. that upon the most strict and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Enquiry they could make, Mr. <hi>Russel</hi> is not Guilty of those Crimes charged upon him in the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amen;</hi> for it cannot be imagin'd but among the most strict and diligent Enquiry they could make, the <hi>Doctors</hi> positive Denyal of being Guilty must be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded: And consequently (if right) he hath cut off all Pretence or Occasion for Repentance and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; Which very well agrees, Does it not, with his former Pretence of Repentance? Either then he repented of no Sin, reformed of no Vice; or now he is a most notorious, and audacious <hi>Scelestique;</hi> So that it is manifest, nothing can be justly Pleaded in his Behalf on Account of any former Zeal, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Repentance and Reformation.</p>
            <p>Lastly, To keep the Matter no longer in Hand; The <hi>Crimes</hi> charged upon the <hi>Doctor</hi> are <hi>true;</hi> if <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible</hi> and <hi>Ocular Evidences</hi> be of <hi>Sufficient Authority:</hi> And the <hi>greatest part</hi> of 'em, and the most <hi>Flagitious</hi> and <hi>Criminal</hi> too, will be <hi>Personally</hi> proved by such <hi>Witnesses;</hi> and the <hi>rest</hi> by those that are every way <hi>Sufficient</hi> and <hi>Sustantial</hi> to <hi>convince</hi> all the <hi>World</hi> of the <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>'em, unless</hi> such as are <hi>prejudiced</hi> and <hi>resolve</hi> be <hi>so;</hi> We say, the <hi>Crimes</hi> charged on the <hi>Doctor</hi> in the <hi>Examen,</hi> will be all <hi>substantially prov'd</hi> upon him, with several <hi>others,</hi> if <hi>he</hi> and his <hi>Friends</hi> shall think their own <hi>Reputation,</hi> or the <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> oblige 'em, to submit their Cause to be Heard and Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd by the generality of the <hi>Baptized Elders</hi> in <hi>London;</hi> or by a competent Number of 'em equally se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected; Time and Place mutually agreed upon; by the <hi>Doctor</hi> and his <hi>Friends</hi> on the one Part, and on the other by one that asketh nothing; but an Impartial Hearing, and Righteous Judgment of the Case.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>NATHANIEL GALE.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:206806:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>